National Geographic
Earth: Making of a Planet
Original Air Date on March 6, 2011
-- sync, corrected by elderman --
Narrator: The Earth, as
far as we know it's the
only home to life
in the universe.
So what makes our
planet so special?
To find answers, we
must travel back in time.
See the first humans
walk the Earth.
Ride each colliding
continent.
Face killer dinosaurs.
Dive into oceans full
of bizarre life forms.
Feel the bitter chill
of global ice ages.
And experience the fury of
cosmic missile attacks.
By travelling
back in time,
we can piece together
our planet's incredible
story.
And discover why all of
this, and all of us,
are here.
The journey starts
almost five billion
years ago.
There's no sign of
Earth just yet.
Only the Sun, a newborn
star surrounded by dust.
The Earth hasn't
formed yet.
But through time,
gravity pulls the dust
into tiny rocks.
To our surprise,
something as complex as
a planet is made from
nothing more than dust
and rocks.
Over millions of years,
gravity pulls these
rocks together to
form the Earth,
one of at least a
hundred planets
circling the sun.
But four and a half
billion years ago,
Earth looks more
like hell than home.
Up close the
temperature is over
2,000 degrees
Fahrenheit.
There's no air, just
carbon dioxide,
nitrogen
and water vapor.
It's so hot and toxic
that if we got any
closer we'd be
incinerated and
suffocated in seconds.
This newborn planet
is a boiling ball of
liquid rock;
an endless ocean of lava.
A young planet called
Theia is heading
straight for Earth.
The size of Mars, it
travels nearly 10 miles
per second, twenty
times faster than a
bullet.
The intruder's gravity
distorts the Earth's surface.
The blast wave races
around the planet.
It's as though both young
planets turn to liquid,
trillions of
tons of debris blast
out into space.
But over the course
of a thousand years,
gravity turns the
rubble into a ring of
red hot dust and rock
that circles the Earth.
From this ring,
a ball forms,
over two thousand
miles wide.
It's the birth
of our moon.
But it's much closer
than the moon today,
just 14,000 miles away
instead of a quarter of
a million miles.
The sun rises over
a cooling Earth.
And sets just
three hours later.
The Earth is spinning
so fast that an entire
day lasts six hours.
The days may pass
quickly but the Earth
changes slowly.
To understand the
making of our planet we
need to fast foard
through millions of years.
3.9 billion
years ago,
a hail of meteors
attack the Earth.
It's debris left over
from the solar system's
formation.
Inside the meteors are
crystals that look like
grains of salt.
And inside the crystals
are minute droplets of
water.
These deadly missiles
could contain the vital
ingredient for
life on Earth.
Only a small amount of
water exists inside
each meteorite, but as
they bombard the Earth
for over 20
million years,
pools of water grow.
The Earth's core
remains molten,
but its surface has
cooled enough to form a
crust.
The air is around
170 degrees.
In the future, there's
a chance we could
swallow
this very water.
Every sip,
every puddle,
every drop of water
in every ocean,
is billions
of years old.
And it may have
travelled millions of
miles to reach us,
carried inside a
meteor.
The Earth looks
more familiar,
but it's still a
dangerous place.
Winds are faster than
the most destructive
hurricanes today.
It's a mega storm,
whipped up by the
planet's rapid
rotation.
The moon is so close to
Earth that its gravity
is overwhelmed,
creating huge tides
that race across the
planet's surface.
But over time, the
moon moves away,
the waves calm down
and the planet spins slower.
700 million years after
the planet's birth,
life-giving water
covers its surface.
And scattered
throughout are tiny
islands.
They seem to have
appeared from nowhere.
So how did
they get here?
Molten rock bursts
through the Earth's
crust and rises up
through the ocean.
Over time the
lava cools,
forming a
volcanic island.
In the future, these
islands will join
together to form the
first continents.
Earth now has
water and land.
It's beginning to look like
the planet we call home.
But the atmosphere is
still toxic and the
temperature
is scorching.
Life here is
impossible.
Narrator: Since the
planet's formation,
meteors have been
pummeling Earth.
But now, 3.8
billion years ago,
the assault enters a
violent new phase.
Something's disturbed
the orbits of these
meteorites.
In addition to water,
the meteors carry
something else.
As they dissolve, the
meteorites release
minerals.
Carbon and primitive
proteins made of amino
acids are transported
from outer space to the
bottom of the ocean.
Thousands of feet below
the waves, it is dark,
and close to freezing.
But a dramatic illusion
is taking shape.
Underwater chimneys,
spewing hot liquid.
Seawater seeps down
into the Earth through
cracks in the crust,
collecting minerals and
gases along the way.
This potent mixture is
released back out into
the ocean, building
these towers.
Combined with the
minerals and chemicals
from the meteorites,
the water becom a
chemical soup.
It's impossible to
know how or when,
but somehow these
chemicals come together
to create life.
The water is now
full of microscopic
organisms.
These single-celled
bacteria are the
earliest forms
of life on Earth.
This is a defining
moment in the making of
the planet.
Microscopic life
is underway.
For hundreds of
millions of years
nothing changes.
The only life is
single-celled bacteria.
To find more
complex life,
we need to fast forward
to 3.5 billion years ago,
and a
shallow ocean.
These look like rocks,
or even plants,
growing out of
the sea bed.
Each mound is a colony
of living bacteria
called a stromatolite.
These bacteria turn
sunlight into food,
a process called
photosynthesis.
It uses the power of
sunlight to traform
carbon dioxide and
water into glucose,
a simple form of sugar.
And this magical
transformation releases
a by-product, a
gas called oxygen.
Underwater, the
stromatolites slowly
fill the oceans
with oxygen.
The oxygen then turns
traces of iron into
rust, which fall
to the ocean floor,
to form deposits
of iron rich rock.
It's this mineral that
will one day be used to
build bridges, ships,
and skyscrapers.
Above the waves, the
oxygen transforms the
atmosphere.
These stromatolites
are creating the most
important element
for life on earth.
Without them, virtually
every living thing
wouldn't exist.
Over the next two
billion years oxygen
levels continue
to rise,
and as the planet's
spin slows,
the days get longer,
lasting at least 16 hours.
3 billion years after
the planet's birth,
there's still no
complex life,
no plants, no
dinosaurs, no humans.
But the Earth has
something unlike any
other planet in
this solar system,
a force with the power
to change everything.
Narrator: One and
a half billion
years ago, the Earth is
a beautiful blue ball,
dotted with
volcanic islands.
Over millions of years,
a mysterious force
rearranges
these islands.
Hidden beneath
the ocean,
the Earth's crust
breaks into vast
plates.
But even deeper, the
Earth's core is so hot
that it generates
movement in the rock
beneath the crust.
These movements push
and pull the plates
around the globe,
carrying the oceans and
islands with them.
Millions of
years race by,
our planet is alive,
and changing.
Over 400 million years
a vast new super
continent takes shape.
It's called Rodinia.
In the shallow waters
surrounding Rodinia,
stromatolites work
their magic for more
than two billion years,
pumping oxygen into the
atmosphere.
The temperature
is 85 degrees.
And the days are
18 hours long.
But this planet looks
more like Mars than Earth.
To find life, we must
fast forward through time.
Washington State: 750
million years ago.
A force deep inside the
planet rips the crust
to pieces.
It's as though the
world is breaking
apart.
And there's only one
force powerful enough
to do this, heat.
It escapes from the
Earth's molten core,
stretching and
weakening the crust.
Inch by inch,
year by year,
the great
super-continent is
splitting in two.
The intense geological
activity spawns a mass
of volcanoes.
They pump carbon
dioxide into the
atmosphere.
The carbon dioxide
mixes with water,
and creates acid rain.
When the continent
tore apart,
many rocks
were exposed.
These rocks absorb
the acid rain,
including its
carbon dioxide.
Vast quantities of CO 2
are absorbed out of the
atmosphere.
Now, there's not enough
carbon dioxide in the
air to trap the sun's
heat around the planet.
In just a few
thousand years,
the temperature
plummets to around
minus 60 degrees.
This frozen wasteland
is Southern Australia,
650 million years ago.
It's the start of what
some scientists call
Snowball Earth, a
period they believe to
be the longest, coldest
ice age ever to grip
the planet.
A vast wall of ice
looms thousands of feet
high.
And it's unstoppable.
The more ice there is
the more sunlight it
reflects away
from the planet,
and the faster
the ice spreads.
Nearby is a second ice
sheet just as high.
The two sheets spread
away from the poles,
toward each other to
meet at the Equator.
Now an ice
sheet up to 10,000
feet thick covers
the entire planet.
Earth first began as a
molten ball of fire,
now it's a frozen
ball of ice.
Virtually all the sun's
light, and warmth,
reflects back
into space.
And it seems as
though nothing,
not even the Sun can
rescue the planet now.
Narrator: 650
million years ago,
ice entombs the planet.
For 15 million years,
the Earth is a vast
frozen snowball.
But it can't
last forever;
something must release
the Earth from this
frozen prison.
And when it does, who
knows whether life has
survived
beneath the ice.
The surface is frozen
but the core is still
hotter than the
sun's surface.
Volcanoes have been
erupting since the
world began to freeze.
But up until now even
their heat and power
made no impact
on the ice.
Volcanoes pump out
billions of tons of
carbon dioxide.
Before the big freeze,
the Earth's rocks
absorbed most
of the CO2.
But now, with the rocks
smothered in ice,
there's nothing to
absorb the gas.
So it fills the
atmosphere.
Like a blanket, it
traps the sun's warmth
around the planet,
allowing the
temperatures to rise.
Now, after 15
million years,
the ice begins to melt.
It's thought that
during Snowball Earth
the ice pushed
the crust down.
But now, as it melts,
the crust bounces up,
creating fissures
and weak spots,
and more volcanoes.
The volcanoes release
more carbon dioxide and
push the temperature
up even higher.
The melt gathers
momentum.
And oxygen levels rise.
Through a series of
chemical reactions the
ice has created oxygen.
While the planet
was frozen,
the Sun's ultraviolet
rays reacted with water
molecules in the ice,
to produce hydrogen
peroxide, a chemical
rich in oxygen.
Now, as the ice melts,
the hydrogen peroxide
breaks down and
releases massive
amounts of oxygen.
The Earth is waking
up, and it's a very
different place.
600 million years ago,
the atmosphere is
warmer, like
a summer day.
And the days are
about 22 hours long.
Add all this water and
it's the perfect recipe
for life.
Before Snowball Earth,
primitive bacteria
emerged in the oceans.
But surely they
couldn't have survived
an ice age 75 times
longer than the entire
span of human history.
If something
has survived,
then life may be found
where it was last seen,
in the oceans.
Now, 540 million
years ago,
in an ocean
full of oxygen,
those primitive
bacteria have evolved.
A handful must have
clung on through the
big freeze.
There are plants
scattered on the sea
floor.
And something else.
What looks like an
armored slug takes up
residence.
It's called Wiwaxia,
a new generation of
complex multi-celled
organisms.
The Earth enters one
of the most dynamic
periods in its history,
the Cambrian explosion.
Increased oxygen levels
allow creatures to grow
larger and develop
bony skeletons.
There are
worms, sponges,
and these trilobites:
distant relatives of
insects, lobsters,
even scorpions.
Life in the
oceans blossoms.
From microscopic
bacteria, to monsters.
This is Anomalocaris.
Nearly two feet long,
it has large eyes,
razor sharp teeth
and grasping limbs.
All it has to do,
is take its pick.
The trilobite can't
right itself,
its soft belly
is exposed.
Also found in the
sea is Pikaia.
Only an inch
and a half long,
they may be the first
organism with a spine.
Over millions of years,
this simple structure
will evolve into the
spine that keeps us
standing.
Expecting to find
life in ruins,
the oceans are in
fact full of life.
Where trilobites
scavenge and monsters
prowl.
And where creatures
begin to take on
familiar forms.
Beneath the waves there
are already tens of
thousands of plant
and animal species.
The advance of life
seems unstoppable.
Narrator: 460
million years ago,
the plates have
been moving, again.
A new continent now
exists, Gondwana.
It's 90 degrees and
oxygen levels are close
to what they are today.
The land should be
covered with plants and
crawling with
creatures.
But there's
not much here,
besides a few
patches of algae.
There's only one
explanation, the Sun.
It blasts the surface
with deadly radiation,
so the complex life in
the ocean doesn't stand
a chance on land.
But 30 miles up, where
the rays enter the
Earth's atmosphere,
something is happening.
When oxygen meets
the sun's radiation,
it turns into
another kind of gas,
call ozone.
This gas forms a
blanket around the
planet and absorbs
the lethal radiation.
Over 120 million years,
the ozone layer gets
thicker and prevents
more and more radiation
from reaching the
Earth's surface.
Without this layer,
life on land simply
wouldn't exist.
Now, shielded
from radiation,
life takes off.
Small mossy lumps are
the first land plants.
They pump out
even more oxygen.
Levels soar.
375 million years ago,
a new species lives in
the water, swimming.
It's a strange fish
called a Tiktaalik.
It uses its neck to
raise itself up.
And its fins
function as legs,
allowing it to move
out of the water.
This is one of the most
important moments in
the making of
our planet.
Over 15 million years,
creatures like these
evolve.
They grow stronger
limbs and spend more
time out of the water,
where plant life is
exploding.
Until, 360 million
years ago,
their relatives,
called tetrapods,
make the land
their home.
From tetrapods, four
legged vertebrates
evolve into
dinosaurs, birds,
mammals and
eventually humans.
There are mosses and
ferns everywhere,
some at least a
hundred feet tall.
A seed is carried
by the wind.
Until now,
plants reproduced
using spores,
single-celled particles
that need plenty of
water to grow.
But this seed is
miles from water.
This embryonic plant
has its own food and
water supply.
Unlike a spore, this
seed can survive far
from water for
months, even years.
The humble seed spreads
life across the planet.
And each tree and plant
pumps out even more
oxygen.
It's an environment
very much like today.
The planet has
come a long way,
from a lump of burning
rock and dust,
to a blue and green
world bursting with
life.
There are now fish,
plants, and this,
the dragonfly.
It's called Meganeura.
This insect is the
size of an eagle.
What were once legs
have evolved into
wings, extending the
dragonfly's hunting
territory over
a vast area.
There are also
millipedes,
and spiders down there.
These creatures,
called arthropod,
were among the first
to set foot on land
hundreds of millions
of years ago.
They look almost
identical to the bugs
that invade our
homes today.
Except for one
big difference.
Like the Meganeura,
they're monsters.
It's a world
full of giants,
where millipedes
are 6 feet long,
andcorpions are
the size of wolves.
This is because the
oxygen level is much
higher than it is
today,
which allows their
respiratory systems to
be more efficient,
fueling thier bodies to
grow larger.
So far, animals have
been laying their eggs
in the water.
But a lizard-like
creature,
called the hylonomus,
prefers land.
Its eggs contain all
the water and nutrients
that the developing
fetus needs.
The babies grow
in their own
self-contained pond.
The egg is a major
evolutionary
breakthrough.
Allowing animals to
leave the water behind,
and conquer land.
This baby hylonomus
leads the advance,
as a new creature,
the reptile.
Inevitably, with
life, comes death.
Dead plant matter
builds up and decays
into dense
soggy layers.
Over hundreds of
millions of years,
rocks cover
these layers.
And heat from the
Earth's core and
pressure from the
overlying rocks
transform these layers
into seams of coal.
Each lump of coal
burned today is made of
plants that died 300
million years ago.
Amidst the decay,
hidden from sight,
life is stirring.
Soon seeds will
germinate,
plants will grow, and
this wasteland will
live again.
Life seems to have
conquered the planet.
But will it last?
Narrator: A herd of
creatures graze
the Siberian plains,
and they are big.
Evolution takes a
huge leap forward,
small lizards are
now giant reptiles.
These scutosaurs are
distant relatives of
turtles.
If these plant eaters
look this tough,
the carnivores must
be seriously mean.
Like this gorgonopsid.
A perfectly engineered
pre-historic killing
machine.
The gorgonopsid's sabre-teeth
wound the scutosaur.
The predator watches,
as its prey grows
weak from blood loss.
But before it can
make its final move,
something
strange happens.
The ground gets hot.
Enormous pressure builds
beneath the surface,
and lava spews
into the air.
But the lava isn't from
one single volcano,
the entire landscape
is erupting.
It's a flood
basalt eruption.
A massive plume of
mantle rises up from
deep inside the Earth,
and pushes molten rock
out through fissures
in the Earth's crust.
The lush paradise is
now a lifeless hell.
The scutosaurs and the
gorgonopsids are dead.
They're the first
casualties in the
greatest mass
extinction the world
has ever seen, the
Permian Extinction.
On the other side of
the continent Gondwana,
nothing's changed, yet.
It appears to
be snowing,
but the temperature
is about 70 degrees.
It's actually ash,
fallout from the
eruptions some
10,000 miles away.
The ash burns and
suffocates the animals,
killing them
around the world.
Sulphur dioxide from
the eruptions fills the
atmosphere.
As it rains, the gas
turns to sulphuric
acid, and burns
everything it falls on.
What was a local
disaster has now turned
global.
The Siberian eruptions
increase the Earth's
carbon dioxide levels.
The atmosphere
gets hotter.
Water evaporates.
And vegetation dies.
Around the world, life
on land is being wiped out.
And life
in the oceans,
has also been
compromised.
The waters turn pink.
Plants, trilobites, and
predators, disappear.
The new, hotter
atmosphere heated the
oceans and stripped
them of oxygen.
Now, this pink algae
is one of the few life
forms that can survive
in the stagnant water.
The Siberian eruptions
transform the entire
planet, nothing, not
even the deepest ocean
floor, is beyond
their reach.
Bubbles of methane gas
escape from beneath the
sea bed.
Methane is a
greenhouse gas,
at least twenty times
deadlier than carbon dioxide.
Until now, the gas
has been frozen.
But as the sea
temperature rises,
it begins to melt.
Released into
the atmosphere,
this powerful gas
pushes up temperatures
even further.
It's now almost
105 degrees,
11 degrees hotter than
before the Siberian
eruptions.
Creatures that survive
the initial destruction
now face a new and
deadly environment.
Few will live.
It's been five hundred
thousand years since
the eruptions
first began,
And all this time, the
lava's been pouring out.
By now, it covers an
area the size of the
United States with a
layer of molten rock
nearly 4 miles deep.
95 per cent of the
species are gone.
A few survive by eating
anything they can find
and living in
burrows underground.
But everything
else, is dead.
250 million years ago,
the Earth reverts back
to an almost
lifeless planet.
But that's about
to change, again.
Narrator: It's
been fifty million
years since virtually
all life on Earth was
wiped out.
And the planet has
been transformed.
It's now 200
million years ago,
and just one
supercontinent, Pangea,
stretches from
pole to pole.
After the trauma of
the mass extinction,
the planet heals.
Temperatures stabilize;
the acid rain
neutralizes and
vegetation returns.
With 95 per cent of all
life on Earth wiped
out, the field opens
for a new species to
emerge.
One that will dominate
the planet like no
other.
The dinosaurs.
These are called
Ammosaurs.
Like all dinos, they
evolved from the
reptiles that survived
the Permian Extinction.
At 15 feet tall, their
size makes them slow,
and vulnerable.
Nearby is the
dilophosaurus.
It's small,
and fast.
The ammosaurus is too
big a meal for one
dilophosaurus.
But not for two.
The dinosaurs have
repopulated the Earth.
But no species can
tame this restless,
volatile planet.
The earth's crust
is thinning.
It's releasing lava
and shaking with
earthquakes, as if
being stretched by some
unseen force.
It's also happening
near what will become
North America's
eastern seaboard.
The Earth's plates are
on the move again.
190 million years
ago, the great
super-continent of
Pangea tears apart.
A vast slab of
land breaks away,
creating a chasm.
It fills with a new
ocean called the Tethys
over what will one day
be the Middle East.
Currents push
nutrients up into
the coastal waters.
And the nutrients
attract fish,
in the millions.
But again, with so much
life, also comes death.
Dead fish and plankton
carpet the ocean floor.
Over the next 10
million years,
layers of rock
will bury and heat
the dead creatures.
Ancient fish and
plankton will
become oil.
Every gallon of
gas in our cars,
every piece of plastic
on the planet,
the paint on our walls,
the carpet under our
feet, even the
soap we wash with,
almost all originated
in this way.
180 million years ago,
the North American
plate is still moving
away from the European
and Asian plate.
It's shifting about
one inch each year,
the same speed at which
our fingernails grow.
But fast forward 35
million years and a new
ocean forms, as well
as new continents.
The United States
breaks away from
Africa.
The world as we
know it takes shape.
The chasm between the
two continents fills,
creating the
Atlantic Ocean.
And in the middle,
lies a volcano.
Like before, currents
deep beneath the
Earth's crust move
the plates again.
The entire sea floor
tears in two and is
pushed up into
a ridge of
mountains and volcanoes.
It grows higher
than the Himalayas,
and longer than
the Rockies.
The water here is hot,
as molten lava forces
its way out from deep
inside the earth.
As the lava cools, it
creates a new range of
volcanic mountains,
and a new ocean floor.
Pangea breaks apart,
and our world
rearranges again.
It's this geological
activity that makes the
Earth restless,
creative and unique.
And every time the
planet reinvents
itself, its inhabitants
adapt and evolve.
Like the ichthyosaurs.
Their reptile ancestors
lived on land,
but as the
planet changed,
so did these
animals.
They grew fins and
moved into the newly
formed Atlantic Ocean.
This one is
20 feet long,
and can travel at a
quick 25 miles an hour.
It's the ocean's
fastest creature and
most efficient
predator.
It rules the oceans
for 50 million years.
But now, there's
a new contender.
The pliosaur.
Longer than a bus, and
as heavy as a truck,
its jaws are eight
times more powerful
than a great
white sharks',
with teeth 12
inches long.
The Earth, and
its inhabitants,
have changed beyond
recognition.
This was once
solid ground,
now it's the
Atlantic Ocean.
The very spot where
ammosaurs grazed and
dilophosaurs
stalked their prey.
The dinosaurs' world
may be different,
but they're as
dominant as ever.
They appear invincible.
Narrator: They're one
of the planet's most
successful species.
They've survived
volcanic eruptions,
earthquakes, and entire
continents splitting
apart, The dinosaurs
have thrived for 165
million years.
A number of mammals
have also survived,
like this
shrew-like animal.
They're prey to
the dinosaurs.
So they live in trees
or underground,
and venture out
only at night.
Mammals pose no threat
to the dinosaurs.
Nothing on Earth
can challenge their
dominance.
Nothing, on Earth.
A large piece
of space rock,
heads toward Earth.
This asteroid is at
least 6 miles across,
and travelling over
40,000 miles an hour.
It's bigger than
Mount Everest,
and heads straight for
the Gulf of Mexico.
It travels so fast that
its impact would be
missed in a
blink of an eye.
A split second changes
the world forever.
At impact, the
asteroid's back edge
stands at 35,000 feet.
It strikes with such
immense force that it
destroys
everything it hits.
The asteroid itself
instantly vaporizes,
unleashing the
energy of millions
of nuclear weapons.
Nowhere is safe,
with debris flying
everywhere.
Debris as big as
entire city blocks
circle the Earth.
The blastwave races out
from the impact zone
like shrapnel from
an exploding bomb.
Minutes after impact,
hundreds of miles
from where the
asteroid struck,
the earth is
under attack.
Boulders rain down.
Earthquakes
shake the ground.
And tsunamis
batter the coasts.
But the onslaught
has only just begun.
The plume of molten
rock and dust spreads
out, and engulfs
the planet.
The entire sky acts
like a giant lamp,
heating the
Earth's surface to
over 500 degrees.
Vegetation
spontaneously ignites.
Even months
after the impact,
smoke and ash
still block out
the sun's rays.
And with less sunlight,
plants die and the
animals starve.
65 million years ago,
the impact has blasted,
stoned and burnt
the dinosaurs.
Their 165 million year
reign is over.
But the dinosaur's
demise brings
opportunity for
another species.
A mammal.
By living underground,
mammals have avoided
the heat and fires.
And by eating anything,
they thrive while more
selective eaters die.
They're the unlikely
inheritors of the
dinosaurs' crown.
And as one story ends.
Another begins.
With the dinosaurs
out of the way,
our ancestors' may now
have a chance, at life.
Narrator: The dinosaurs
are long dead.
The planet is peaceful.
In this new
world, our mammal
ancestors are evolving.
47 million years
ago, this lake,
in what will one
day be Germany,
is the perfect
place to spot them.
Unlike earlier
mammals, its eyes and
brain are bigger.
This is Darwinius
Massilae, or Ida.
She looks nothing
like humans,
but fossil evidence
today indicates that
these creatures might
evolve into monkeys,
apes, and
eventually humans.
Looking back through
47 million years of
evolution might reveal
one of our earliest
known ancestors.
The lake sits on a
volcanic crater.
It belches out
noxious gas,
that eventually
kills Ida.
The lake preserves
her in its
oxygen depleted depths.
One day, when the water
is gone and Ida's
fossil is found, this
primitive primate could
help piece together the
beginning of our own
story, the story
of human life.
We're closer to
understanding how
everything we've seen,
from ocean bacteria,
through walking fish
and subterranean
rodents, leads to us.
And to understanding
how our
planet was made.
47 million years
ago, the atmosphere
is much like today.
The temperature
is 75 degrees.
And a day lasts
just under
twenty four hours.
The Earth is now
almost identical to
the planet we call home.
Almost.
The Earth's plates are
on the move again.
India moves north
toward Asia.
The Indian and Asian
plates are locked
in a titanic struggle,
and neither plate
is winning.
As they buckle, the
ocean floor contorts
upward along a
1,500 mile line.
A vast mountain
range rises up
over 27,000 feet.
These are the
Himalayas.
And the highest
mountain of all,
Mount Everest.
Its summit reaches
up into the
Earth's jet stream,
the same altitude
where planes fly.
When the snow on
the peaks melts,
it feeds rivers like
the Ganges, Indus,
Yellow and Yangtze.
The Himalayas are like
a vast water tower.
One day, their rivers
will supply water for
almost half the
world's population.
20 million years ago,
this is our planet,
with every continent,
and every ocean
as we know it.
Except one thing
is still missing,
the human race.
And for humans
to evolve,
something needs
to change.
Narrator:
Along the African
coast, a great
rift opens up.
It stretches
nearly 4,000 miles,
with mountains growing
along its edge.
This ape-like creature
may stay in these trees
forever, but its
world is changing.
The growing mountains
act like a wall,
prohibiting moisture
from the Indian Ocean
from passing
over the land.
It's getting
hotter, and drier.
The lush rainforest
becomes an arid
savannah.
The new hotter climate
changes the creatures'
habitat, forcing them
to search further for
food, soon, they stop
dragging their knuckles
like apes.
And begin to stand,
and walk on two feet.
It's the most
important step in
the human story.
This mountain range
could be the reason
humans
walk on two feet.
The random movement of
two plates may have
kick-started a chain of
events that leads to
the first humans.
A man and child.
A scene very
much like today.
But it's one and a half
million years ago.
They are an early
species of human called
Homo Erectus.
And these are the first
footprints like our
own; civilizations
past and present,
everyone that's
ever lived,
the greatest
inventions,
the most
brilliant ideas.
Human history, in all
its complexity and
splendor, begins
here and now.
The climate
changes again.
70,000 years ago
sea levels fall.
And the gap between
Africa and Arabia
shrinks to just
eight miles.
The Red Sea is now
narrow and shallow
enough for a small
group to cross,
out of Africa.
They're another later
species of human,
called Homo Sapiens.
Scientists believe that
the entire world beyond
Africa was populated
from descendants of
these two hundred
individuals.
Over time our ancestors
multiply and spread
out; to India, onto
Asia and into Europe.
But while humans
head north,
a giant wall of
ice travels south.
Europe, 40,000
years ago.
Homo sapiens arrive,
only to find a world
that's quickly
changing.
It should be the
height of summer,
but it's
getting colder.
The plants are
frostbitten,
and the rivers
are frozen.
Natural changes in
the Earth's orbit,
CO2 levels, and the
flow of warm water
around the planet
conspire to lower the
Earth's temperature.
The Earth, and
its inhabitants,
enter an ice age.
Glaciers as high as
skyscrapers creep over
the northern hemisphere
about a foot every day,
Slow, and powerful,
they sculpt the
landscape, gouging out
great depressions.
The planet will never
look the same again.
Now, around twenty
thousand years ago,
they grind to a halt.
Much of the northern
hemisphere is covered
by ice sheets up to one
and a half miles thick.
With trillions of
gallons of water locked
up as ice, sea
levels fall.
A strip of land emerges
from the ocean between
Siberia and Alaska.
It's a bridge between
two vast continents,
a gateway that takes
humans from Asia to a
new world,
the Americas.
They're the last great
continents to be
colonized, the last
great human migration,
and the first
Americans.
Now, 14,000 years
ago, the changes that
triggered the
ice age reverse.
As the ice retreats,
it reveals a very
different northern
hemisphere.
The huge depressions
that the glaciers
create fill with
water to become North
America's Great Lakes.
6,000 years ago, the
ice retreats back to
the poles, toward the
Arctic and Antarctic.
After a four and a half
billion year journey,
we're, finally home.
This is our
world, our time.
The planet's incredible
story helps us
understand how and why
everything around us is
here today.
From the skies above.
To water, the essential
ingredient for life.
To the ground
beneath our feet.
And finally life,
a chain of catastrophes
and coincidences,
creating a
spectacular result.
Each triumph and
disaster is a step
leading to here,
each and every one of
us, right now.
But the Earth's
story isn't over.
This journey is only
half the story.
A lot more is
yet to come.
The Earth will live for
at least another 4.5
billion years.
More wonders,
more terrors,
and more strange
creatures lie ahead for
our restless and
creative planet.
The next chapter of
Earth's story is still
to be written.
-- sync, corrected by elderman --